the
[Music]
welcome to mental health Mondays it's so
good to see each and every one of you
back here today at the beginning of your
week on a Monday to discuss things about
your mental health just want to say
welcome to my co-host Dr Ricardo white
always good to see you here and to be
here with you same to you good to see
you sis yes and so I we want to see
where you guys are viewing from and
where yeah where you're watching from I
know when I logged in about maybe uh 15
minutes before the program started I saw
that some of you were already on there
and I saw Clint was on Clint was not the
very first one and I don't know if I'm
saying it right but Clint you were a
second so very good we can't we can't
have this continue Agnes I don't I don't
know congratulation Agnes yes looks like
Agnes got there just a little bit before
Clint and they were greeting each other
so we're good glad and happy to see both
of you um and please those of you that
are on right now please share on your
social media uh the link to our program
for this evening because we are doing
part two to the disease uh the disease
to please we're T doing part two uh last
week went uh really well with all your
questions and I just want to ask you
guys um were you thinking about it this
week did you was did you some of the
things that we were talking about did
did you um actually process some of that
this week just put a one in the chat if
the topic really was uh something that
uh had you thinking about it this week I
hope so hope so you could put a one in
the chat if that is the case but um I
want to say
welcome some of you do we have all right
thought I saw a place well welcome to
all of you but please put in the the
chat where you're viewing from I don't
see any
locations but some of you are chatting
in the chat so welcome so I don't know
where you're viewing from but we are
just glad to have you here please share
on your social media you know mental
health is just everybody talks about
mental health and the importance of
mental health and I think it's so
amazing that um we are able to do mental
health programming every week um not
just for our church people but for for
everyone this is for this is for the
world this is international this is for
whoever can um just just log on and tune
in and hear and so this is such an
important topic that the topics that we
cover mental health it's so important uh
and we want you to share this with the
world because this is everybody is
impacted by this but yeah what are your
thoughts about that Dr White and I am
trying to talk as loud as possible
hopefully you guys are are hearing me
okay great you sound great there's no
volume issues um yeah uh you're you're
just hearing that mental health is at
the center of the discussion uh nowadays
and I man what a great what a great book
I think you guys are really going to
enjoy some of the points that we bring
out in this book the disease uh to
please um maybe you might give a little
refresher on what was what what was your
introduction to this book yes you know I
you know what really
the introduction to this book is I had
so I was seeing so many clients I've had
so many people come in and just talk
about uh this issue they don't actually
come in and talk about the issue of
being a people pleaser they talk about
other issues and through that um it's
discovered by them and by me that they
indeed are people Pleasers and the the
issues that that is causing them in
their life the stress and unhappiness
that no one really knows that they feel
and are going through uh but they know
they know how it's impacting them so
that's doing research on that to try to
help them is what got me to this book
the disease to
please it just shows you the power of
caring that it You You You Came Upon
such a powerful
resource um but uh I think I think you
guys are going to love some of the the
the points um that we cover in this book
we shall we just jump into it or what
are your thoughts yeah well I just
wanted just to for those who are here
for the first time if there's those here
for the first time and that you weren't
here last week just want you to know
that this is by Dr Harriet B breier um
and that she is the author of this book
and uh she has some really great points
and today we're not just going to be
talking about the issue of being a peop
pleaser but also we're going to look at
some of the solutions that she brings
out in the book that can help you um if
you are dealing with this issue so so
yeah we're going to we're going to Jump
Right
In we're going to jump right in and um
and some people and I did I thought
about this before the program started I
was just like uh doing some things and I
just came across my mind that I was like
I don't know if we were clear because I
was listening to her chapter five in
chapter five she talks about
um you know not if you are being abused
or you're in a in a situation where
you're being abused you know even
physically phys physically and
emotionally that is not uh that it's not
a good thing to be kind in that and to
be a people pleaser in that
situation um and so we want you know I
just wanted to make sure that we're very
clear that um in that situation you need
to to step away and not continue to be
in that situation because that is that
is harming you and you know it can be
can be very harming so I just don't know
if we were clear on that last week and
so I just thought I was gonna make that
very clear as we start no that's that's
I mean it's it's it's critical because
in there might be some other resources
that will encourage you to make life
about somebody else okay that's not this
book
book is reminding you to prioritize
yourself um and and also what one of the
things that we talked about last week
was checking your motives check your
motives yes why why are you people
pleasing and one of the things a book
highlights is that part of why people
are people pleasing is often the fear of
rejection the fear of being alone so
we're talking about fear based
um behavior and when things are
fear-based you're often aren't going to
get the best uh outcome so so getting at
the core of why you're behaving the way
that you're behaving is very very
important uh to getting to some of these
Solutions you're gonna talk about Dr
tante yes well thank you for making me a
doctor but I'm not a doctor you're Dr
White yeah always have to always have to
clarify that for for people but um yes
no and I just to like break this down
like in a way where people are really
getting it meaning like if if you are
some of you may be thinking like well I
just like to do nice things nice things
for people am I a people pleaser if your
motivation is coming from just a pure if
there's no fear there if there's no um
distorted thoughts that are saying oh if
I don't do this they won't like me or
this is how I am loved by people and
this defines me I'm not good enough just
on my own so I have to do things for
people all the time for them to want to
be my friend or want to be around me if
if none of that is involved and there's
no fear then do a kind thing and you
know say yes when you can say um you
know say you know tell people yeah I can
do that for you but if you're doing it
and the emotion of fear is a part of it
you are most likely a people pleaser and
I just want to um just go over some key
points that she brings out um
understanding the roots of the people
pleaser understanding the roots on
how someone can get to this space um
recognize that people pleasing often
this is what she shares in her book is
that recognizing that people pleasing
often stems from low
self-esteem fear of rejection or desire
for
approval she asked a question in the
book she says reflect on your childhood
experiences that may have contributed to
your need to please
others and I love that she asked that
question in the book because sometimes
we just don't just stop and and pause
and take some time I mean when we're in
therapy when we go to therapy when
people go to therapy they do that but
sometimes but a lot of time if you're
not in that type situation you don't
take the time to just think why do I do
this what started this type of behavior
for me how did I start thinking like
this what are my triggers why do I do
these things and so even now as this
program is going you might be thinking
of how if you feel like you're dealing
with this issue how did you get here and
I think it's very
powerful to take that time I don't know
if you're muted this is this is so this
is so like deepr rooted though because
how many times have sometimes you're
you're walking and you encounter a
person who has kids right and they're
like say hello to the nice man and you
see the little kids like you know no and
I'm like they don't have to say hello to
me I am nobody important to them and
that is perfectly okay but like cuz I
know that's what I tried to reinforce
with my daughter it's like you like
saying hello go ahead and you say hello
you don't feel like saying hello you
don't have to say hello right like it's
in it's it's when we're kids that how
many times was were our parents like say
hello and you're like I don't even know
who that is there's something in me
that's telling me that I shouldn't you
know and you tell them and so it's
almost like we were conditioned for this
to neglect what our body is telling us
and just do it anyway when in fact no as
children sometimes we should be back up
like you if you don't feel like doing it
maybe you don't have to now of course
you can take it to an extreme and I'm
not talking about taking it to that
extreme where you know you can be rude
nobody's talking about being rude but
it's it's acquainting you with who you
are and understanding that your no is
Meaningful and your desire to say no is
is is Meaningful obviously in the
context of respectfulness and obedience
also I get that but this is a separate
discussion where we're talking about
sometimes kids are raised as if they
don't have the right to having feelings
they don't have a right to they don't
have agency in terms of how they're
going to interact with an adult and for
those of you with young children be
intentional about providing agency some
agency and and weighing that careful you
know tight rope of making sure kids are
respectful but at the same time they
have agency they're enti to how they
feel yes yes and I think we talked about
this a little bit last week maybe we did
touch on it
just um in certain well just in general
I was going to say I was going to talk
about different cultures and they it
looks you know a little bit different in
different cultures being um in for this
situation but really just in general I
mean
because and it's it's such a fine
balance of teaching your children um how
to be respectful and obedient and all of
those things that's what parents are
trying to do but we take sometimes we go
so far with
that take them out of that that healthy
space of just you know them feeling like
they can actually say how they
feel um or do not have to do something
that they're not comfortable with and
then that just stays with them like okay
well I'm I have to do these things to
make people like me I have to do these
things to make somebody happy even
though I don't want to do it this was a
good uh comment uh that ammer made and I
think a lot of people can resonate with
it resonate with this my roote was being
bullied in middle school and once I
became semi-popular in high school I was
so afraid to losing all my new friends
that I did everything to keep them man I
feel your pain sis yeah like who
wouldn't you know who wouldn't so so but
it it's a it's a tight rope but I I
guess the point that I was really
getting at is look at how early it
starts it starts so early where
sometimes we're cultivated into this um
I gotta be a nice person I I'm gonna I
don't have agency to tell you no um I
don't really feel like that right now
that doesn't make you a bad person so
yeah we're not trying to raise rude kids
please don't hear that that's not that's
not what we're talking about but we're
talking about the power of agency and
the power of getting in tune with how
you're feeling and feeling like you have
a right to it Clint said um it's hard to
find a balance for ourselves let alone
for our kids let alone for our kids you
know I I think I've tried to use my
child my childhood experience growing up
to to pause reflect and say well what's
the experience I want my daughter to
have uh given the experience I had what
were the things I like what were the
things I didn't like right and I I this
was important agency was very important
I was raised in the regime of be seen
and not heard like this kind of stuff
you know um and uh I mean we we were
conditioned to people please I would say
and and this book
highlights that it's dangerous it's
dangerous so many of us are at risk of
burnout and at the seat of burnout we
talked about this last week at the seat
of it is these noble goals like Amar
just said I want everyone to love me um
I want to be a a boss that's loved and
appreciated and you know just all this
different stuff um not realizing that
some of these Noble Ambitions can set us
up for Burnout if we really and truly
don't set boundaries that protect our
sanity yes and learning I mean between
yes learning how to set boundaries
it it's so difficult for people to learn
that especially people Pleasers because
again a boundary would be just a
beautiful no yeah that being able to
exercise the beautiful no and this is
the thing you're saying the reason why
the know is beautiful is because you're
not being you're not saying it in a rude
way like you want to be you want to make
sure that whoever's asking you to do
what they would like for you to do but
you don't want to do you're staying it
with a kind uh respectful tone and all
of those things no can be hurtful when
the way we say it is rude and hurtful
and so uh people just people Pleasers
definitely stay far away from the no
because they're just like that's mean
and no is only bad when you say it in a
mean way right and and at the core of a
beautiful know is oh let me take the
time to understand you and what you're
asking let me really make sure that I'm
giving this every chance I can um and
then after I've taken the time to really
understand it then I can meaningfully
now declare why it's you you it's not in
your best interest that I do this and it
certainly is not in my best interest
that I do this but you can now you might
even be able to get consensus and the
person's like yeah you're you're right I
probably have a better option so so
that's the beauty of the no um one of
the things she talks about is saying yes
comes at a cost yes saying yes comes at
a cost um and uh there's a there's a
there's a marketer that I enjoy quite a
bit name is Jeff Walker and I've heard
him say your yes must be defended by a
thousand
NOS your yes must be defended by a
thousand NOS or saying knows to set you
up for the yes that you want to say yes
to yes yes yes yes yes that's yeah
that's powerful that's powerful just
want to remind you uh guys that you're a
part of this conversation like we want
your
questions um and definitely your
comments as well so we know you're
commenting uh some in the chat so please
put your questions um up so that we
would love to bring your questions into
the discussion one to also some of the I
um some of the things that she talks
about to to be able to help the people
pleaser is identifying your triggers
identifying your triggers keep a journal
she talks about keeping a journal to
note situations where you feel compelled
to please others including your thoughts
and feelings during these times like how
are you feeling you're feeling the fear
but why why are you feeling afraid so
you're looking at what triggers
you yeah I mean I think that's just
powerful because this is part of
self-awareness
and you know once once you get clear on
your triggers it protects you from
falling subject being U hijacked by your
triggers right Deborah goes would you
say some people are people pleasing to
keep the peace in their relationship
what is the danger in doing this uh
based on fear yeah Deborah you're afraid
you're gonna lose but go ahead so here
was was here was the point that I that
was on the tip of my tongue Deborah so
you just brought it out um listen to
this one avoiding conflict weakens
relationships avoiding conflicts weakens
relationship and to further explain it
ironically trying to please everyone
often leads to weaker relationships
because people Pleasers suppress their
true feelings leading to passive
aggressiveness or resentment oh I'm
sorry I'm so late you know traffic man
we in Southern California you knew about
the traffic man stop it you know um yeah
so now as opposed to us dealing with the
issue um instead we were passive
aggressive and yeah you you kind of want
to you want to you want to deal with the
things in an honest and upfront fashion
now this is the this is what I learned
in the book uh crucial
conversations that it is actually an
honor to have a crucial conversation
with a person now while I'm saying this
to you I already know there are people
that you don't feel like you can trust
with hey this is how I feel about you
okay so I already know that and you
obviously have to be judicious about
this
but part of how you can set up a crucial
conversation is I want to talk to you
about this issue because I care about
this relationship right I want to talk
to you because I care about this
relationship I'm really afraid you're
going to misunderstand me but the
relationship is so important to me it's
worth the
risk it's worth the risk so so I'm I'm
going to be vulnerable and I'm going to
take the risk of being misunderstood no
one likes to be misunderstood and that's
why a lot of times people run the other
way but again what ends up happening is
you become passive aggressive well no I
care about you I value this relationship
so I'm gonna risk it and and and let you
know these are this is how I'm feeling
and I'd like to hear from you how you're
feeling yes I I love what you just
shared and so to even go and to go back
to
Deborah's um question and statement
again everything you said Dr White
100% um you know it's like it's not I
teach my couple clients and even every
individuals as well that um don't
suppress your feelings it's not how
you're feeling and discussing it with
whoever you need to talk to it is how
you do it so we always think that a
conflict or um has to be done in an ugly
way I'm sorry guys it was too in our
face on Friday I have to say this I'm
sorry as a therapist and just as a a
human it was two in our face I have to
say this um what we saw on Friday
between the two presidents um and the
vice president is
exactly how it is not supposed to be
done that they they don't agree on
whatever but the way they dealt with it
even their the body language I'm sorry
guys I watched it a lot of times the
body language uh the way they spoke to
each other that's not how you deal with
conflict or if you have a difference of
opinion or tell just sharing something
with someone on how you feel like they
were talking over each other you see
what I'm saying like all of these type
of things so when you're when you need
to share and talk to somebody and you
know that there's a conflict of at least
you guys have a difference of opinion or
you need to share how you
feel that is an example of exactly how
you do not do it you just you are to be
respectful um I think I've talked about
on here I like to teach people how to to
have discussions these type of
discussions with empathy and
understanding so that even means your
body language that means like how you
know you're coming to the person they're
supposed to be listening to you with an
empathetic heart and then when it's
their turn to talk you're doing the same
thing you know it's like you don't talk
over each other so that's the type of
way that you uh if you don't want to do
something you can discuss it in that
type of manner so you're not being a
people pleaser bringing this back to
people pleasing you're but you're able
to have that discussion with somebody in
that type of healthy way not like the
example that we saw on Friday so I had
to just say that well it's it's
interesting because one of the things
that you saw missing from the
conversation was questions that can be
so helpful like what are you hearing me
say what are you hearing me say and
starting my response with you know
here's what I'm hearing you say like th
like I can't tell you how many arguments
I've been able to calm down just with
you know what let's pause for a second
let's make sure we're tracking like what
are you hearing me say like I found that
just so interesting
um but yeah what are your thoughts yes I
have thoughts about that but we have
another question too so we'll go to
there it says does this happen with
parents uh where you do everything they
say to please them but you're not given
the power to say no or have an opinion
can this be a
trigger um to please later in life
absolutely absolutely read that one more
time does this happen with parents where
you where you're just yeah this person
doing everything to please their parents
but they don't in that relationship they
don't have a right to say no can this um
bring about becoming a people pleaser
and be a and be um can this be a trigger
later in
life did did you I mean like did you let
your kids and that's interesting because
with healthy parenting my kid absolutely
had the right um had the right to say no
to certain things you know right you
know hey do you want to do this do you
want like it was one of those things
it's just that in addition to that they
also came were to understand well there
are certain things that I'm not asking
you about so for example am I going to
consult with you as to whether or not
all the doors need to be locked that's
not up to you you know we we're not
looking for your opinion on on that
matter so there are some life and death
issues where uh it's healthy for a child
to understand the boundaries and guess
what that's how life is there are things
your company wants your input on and
there are things your company does not
need your input on and that's just the
way it works and there are things in
your life that you want your company's
input on and there are things your
company does not get to have any input
on um so so there is a dayon there is a
giv and take but yeah in a in a
healthy uh parenting
situation there there should be moments
where you have the right to say no and
then there are other moments where no
this does not fall within your perview
right um if there's a burglar that will
not be your problem that'll be my
problem you know um so just want to
balance that out no and it's yeah it's
um okay we have another one let's Okay
um so Cassie says good evening all I try
to please I try to please people so they
wouldn't say oh she says she's a
Christian um and did X Y and Z and I
didn't want to cause a bad reflection to
others as a
Believer so I mean thank you for that
question because it is a good or you
know not even a question but a good uh
comment because I do know in the
Christian world this is where
a lot of the conflict comes in for a lot
of Christians because they're just like
and this question was a similar question
was asked last week too so even Jesus we
talked about had to go rest for a while
the Bible says he just said you know
come um let's rest for a while meaning
like it wasn't the principle we can get
there it
wasn't even Jesus had to go rest let's
put it that way so you Jesus had to get
he had to get poured into so he could
continue to be the blessing um that he
was to the world and so we as sinful
human beings Jesus wasn't sinful right
so and he needed to go rest and so we as
sinful human beings um with not able to
handle the stress of the world the way
Jesus was able to handle the stress of
the world and I'm meaning like how it
impacts our mental health how it impacts
our mood or or all of those things um
it's important to take care of yourself
it's it's important to do self-care and
set boundaries when you are not able to
do something you are able to say the
beautiful no um and that's a completely
Christian thing to do is to say the
beautiful no in a nice way and you know
let the person know if there's an opport
you know if you're able to do what
they're wanting you to do at another
time and that's possible then you'll be
able to do that um but if this is
something that if you are only if you're
saying yes out of fear or for the
Christian I would say and it is still
fear but we would probably call it
legalism does that make sense well Dr
white I mean obviously obviously it
makes sense um I I would also add to it
that Cassie this is the reason for why
we need as Christians to really
Forge a rich
robust devotional life yes because some
of these questions are really hard hey
what should I do and one of the things a
rich devot devotional life will do is it
will it will help you order your steps
it will attune you to what it is God
would have you do in that situation
because once you're clear on what God
would have you do now you kind of don't
it's out of your hands now it's out of
your hands no this is what this is how
God wants me to handle it and one of the
things that you would see is Jesus was
very very committed to a rich devotional
life and you saw the results like the
way he would Sid step those you know
those those traps um he that is without
sin Let Him cast the first stone I mean
just the perfect responses just knowing
exactly how to make the connections um
and we're told he it's not like he used
his godliness if I suspect it came from
God ordering a steps and and God I
believe can do that for us
as well um so so Cassie that's what can
help you understand moment to moment
sometimes what you should do in that
moment yes I wna and this is really what
we're saying but I want to just say one
of the things that she says in the book
and I just like the way it's put
together is again talking about setting
boundaries learn to say no without
feeling
guilty like no is a complete sentence
yeah yes but with but learning to yes
it's a complete sentence but learning to
say no without feeling guilty I think
that is where a lot of people Pleasers
get stuck there because they don't like
the that feeling for thems either but I
think education and awareness and will
help you to realize you don't have to
allow yourself to feel guilty you have a
choice well the the interesting there
sister tante is how many times has a
person asked you to do something
and you avoided the little twinge like
so you were like okay I'll do it so you
would have felt a little bad maybe for a
little bit but now that you said yes you
feel a lot of bad for the majority of
the time until the commitment and the
whole time you're thinking I shouldn't
be doing this I don't know why I'm doing
this I didn't want to do this I just
didn't want to feel like a bad person
and the whole time rather than just that
little bad that you would have felt and
you would have moved on and every time
you think about it you're like man I'm
so happy that I told them I wouldn't be
able to do it and now I don't have to
give all of my Sundays up for this or
right whatever else it is like there are
other things I was devoted to um and hey
man can I just be as clear as possible
this is not easy stuff that we're
talking about okay we we all have to
take a look at um you know am I saying
yes too much and am I
avoiding um am I avoiding am I being
fearful of a person's response rather
than really tuning into well how do I
feel about it you know but sister at
tante I I believe you have some special
skills and you've developed a measure of
comfort with saying no
now
now that's always been the I have always
this is I'll be honest guys I have
struggles I have other struggles but
this people part I have I don't struggle
here just with this this topic I have
other struggles um and you know I can
say that my husband and I we compliment
each other because he has struggled with
this more transparency he had and yeah
transparency he has struggled with this
more um and so in our relationship we
learned like he is actually I probably
started saying yes a little bit more
because of him and he's definitely
started to say no a lot more because of
me so we always use this analogy that
he's the G and I'm the breaks because
he'll just be like okay yeah you know
yes yes yes he doesn't want some of
these things that we're talking about he
doesn't want to disappoint but you think
of especially the role that he does as a
pastor like he he's someone's always
asking him for something and if he has
to say the beautiful no at times because
he has to pour in for himself he and he
has to pour into our marriage he has to
pour into our children so he needs to
make sure you guys see all these
balloons and all that happening um did
you didn't see that that's I saw the
balloons I but I don't know how you did
it that yeah that new program on on a
Mac anyways I'm sorry but um I was
saying he has to pour into himself pour
into me and pour into our
children um so that first even before he
can pour into the church and the
ministry and everyone else those are the
that has to happen happen so when that
happens he shows up and be is the best
pastor and the best you know um minister
to be able to minister to the world um
and so he had to learn how to balance
that and just like everybody else nobody
we none of us are perfect none of now
why why were you so good at saying
no
um I don't I don't I just CA cuz you're
a mean person no I was just about to say
I I was like I'm not a mean person but
defin let me tell you no but I but I'll
say this transparency here it goes here
it goes transparency you know I'm so
transparent all the time Dr white but um
I I just you know I always you know I
just I probably I was a little I was
spoiled I was raised I was a little
spoiled okay so I mean it's just the
truth it's just the truth I was spoiled
and so um I just basically when I came
into Ministry
it was like I mean that's is where God
wanted me to be to learn some of these
things that he wanted to refine and me
to be able to give so much to others you
know but at times and then we went then
I got so far to where I'm like oh well
we're I'm really we were giving so much
that we did weren't setting the
boundaries for ourselves can can I then
we learned how to do that and that made
Ministry a happy space but then becoming
a therapist took me even to another
level of having having to become even
more empathetic and caring so much about
people so I think between my husband and
becoming a therapist I definitely just
um I learned how to be more on the gas a
little bit um but but can we go back you
you you made an interesting statement
you said um I was spoiled and and I'm
wondering I'm wondering if the truth is
not your you experienced a love that
gave you the confidence to say no like
you didn't feel like you needed to
please people we definitely can look at
it that way yeah because maybe you know
you're growing up and people are like oh
you're so spoiled blah blah blah blah
blah so maybe that's an excellent way to
look at it yeah you're right I did H I
did I did feel that confidence to be
able to say no I wasn't afraid to say no
like yeah no I that's not g to work for
me so when I met my husband and I was
like and I would tell him I was like you
know you don't have to say yes to
everything but I you know people
pleasing that wasn't even on my radar
and um yeah so very very interesting
hold on one second okay all right yeah
so hopefully our transparency is helping
you guys here that's that's the reason
for it um just to let you guys know that
we're not perfect either and you know
these uh things that we share with you
and even with our clients are very
beneficial to us as well uh
but I want to talk about some other
things that she talks about on how to
help the people pleaser uh building
self-esteem because she talked about um
and the first thing that she talked
about how people Pleasers get to where
they are and The Roots uh for people
pleasing and they
recognize um that they don't they their
self-esteem is low a lot of times so
building self-esteem engage in
self-affirmation practices regularly
remind yourself of your worth and
achievements um I love working with my
clients with this with this one doing
affirmations and I have them do
affirmations three times a day and um I
also for their homework three times a
day so depending on what they're going
through is what their affirmations are
going to be but uh I have them look in
the mirror because I want I want them to
see themselves saying it I want them to
hear themselves saying it and I tell
them it's going to feel very awkward
at first it's going to feel like you're
lying to yourself and you're going to
feel like you know it's going to feel
that way and that's okay for it to feel
that way because then eventually it's
not going to feel that way when you are
intentional and when you are are just
doing it every day you're rewiring your
mind you're building new Pathways in
your brain to have a different thought
process because what we learned last
week is um people pleasing has dis a
distorted thought process and so we have
to feed you can't you can't depend on
other people feeding in to you these
positive things you feed positivity into
yourself so you build your self-esteem
needs to be built up and so yeah
positive affirmations what are your
thoughts on that Dr way well
I I'm still back
at the fact that you were raised with
enough love to give you the confidence
to say no and be completely comfortable
with that and so now when a person
doesn't have that what your exercise is
teaching them is well now you've got to
do that for yourself um and
unfortunately we don't understand the
power of our words so we think this is
just a silly exercise no your words cast
spells including over you you know
there's a re reason they say spell the
word um you you do have influence over
your subconscious over your
well-being um and this is why the words
that you say are just so powerful and
the other thing is paying attention to
your selft talk
because what's interesting
is yeah what what's interesting is you
know in scripture where it says um
the the the the out of out of the
abundance of the heart the subconscious
thoughts um you speak and so it really
just kind of
underscores that your words and the and
your selft talk can be an indicator of
what's going on with you
subconsciously and this is the reason
why you then want to control it and you
want to um be sure that you're pouring
good things into your subconscious
because out of the abundance of what you
put in there is what's going to come out
of you um and you and you can control
that process yes yes I see some people
in the chat saying that's hard when we
were start talking about
affirmations uh Michelle it it is hard
and at first it's it can be at first it
can be hard it can be again like you're
going to feel like you're lying to
yourself it's going to feel awkward all
of those things but just like anything
else we continue to do something um on
you know on a daily basis even we put it
we continue to do that hard work and it
might hurt at first might be difficult
at first but you're going to get you're
going to benefit from that it's just
like starting to work out at the gym
again it might be hard to start picking
up those weights but as you continue to
do it it gets easier I was just thinking
just today I had a client that I was
talking about this with with um and
doing some
affirmations um okay all right so yeah
so I have I had a client today that I
was dealing with and I could tell when I
um let me just pause so I think Dr White
is going to have to step away right now
okay so and to deal with something
that's very important and so we praying
for whatever it is and hope that it'll
be taken care of in is okay thank you so
much he will be back with us um next
week thank you so much okay thank you
thank care bye bye okay bye bye um but
okay so let's um again I was um working
with somebody today and I was telling
them their affirmations for them I mean
the affirmations are catered to their
situation and I could see in this young
man's face like I was saying the
positive affirmations to him and to that
this is what what I wanted him to work
on throughout the week and I could see
him he just he didn't say this is going
to be hard his face told me that this
was going to be so hard almost like he
was afraid to say these words and so to
say these things and um that's how his
brain is currently wired but as he
continues to do this every day that he
will start to unwire his brain and his
thought processes are going to start to
be different um and that is the
beautiful thing about pouring into to
yourself so again it will it it will be
it can be hard but it's so important to
build that self-esteem so that again you
can feel confident and feel okay with
saying no and not feeling guilty when
you have to say the beautiful no it's
not saying no it's saying it
beautifully and um not feeling guilty
about it and knowing that learning to
know that you don't have to you don't
have to say yes to everybody all the
time and learning to pour into yourself
so again we still have time for some
questions um but I also want to uh just
go over some of the things that she
lists that can help um challenging
negative beliefs oh I love this one
challenging negative beliefs identify
the challenge and identify and challenge
negative beliefs about yourself that
fuel people uh fuel people pleasing
Behavior replace negative selft talk
with positive
affirmations this I love teaching people
on how to do this there's the we just
talked about the
affirmations um and but to replace those
that negative selft talk that negative
selft talk is what is causing your low
self-esteem it's the negative self selft
talk now the negative selft talk didn't
come out of nowhere so circling back
about what Dr White was saying um or
even what uh the author of this book was
saying too like going back and finding
out when did this start when did this
start in your life um and so that
negative selft talk
started as a child I I can tell you that
most of these foundational issues that
adults are dealing with people pleasing
um whatever you feel in the issue it
started at a young age so whatever
happened in your childhood that taught
you that or you you you grew to um
believe that this this whatever your
negative thinking about that you say to
yourself whatever situation caused you
to start thinking that way so many times
starts in childhood so an am actually
brought up her statement it was in
Middle School do you know how many times
I have heard Middle School in therapy
Middle
School I mean we all have to go to
Middle School right but it is that time
of course we all think like hi school is
the time where Middle School is just a
time in young people's lives where so
many things are formed around that 11 12
year old because you just you're not a
teenager you're not a little kid people
are being mean or people dress this way
you don't look like that it's so many
things that happen during that time in
people's lives that they start to create
this negative selft talk uh which causes
insecurity which can which can cause
people
pleasing so
uh those are just and the thing is the
affirmations saying the affirmations
again can rewire and help you start to
say positive things that's why the
affirmations are so important the
affirmations are so important because
that negative selft talk is just on like
I don't know if this is a term but
autoplay okay I just made that up or
maybe it's a real term I don't know um
but um it's just on autoplay it's just
always going in your mind right you have
to be intentional and mindful enough and
and be aware enough to
stop to push
stop and then pour positive affirmations
into your mind because and it's been on
autoplay for years so you're trying to
recreate Pathways in your brain where
this negative self talk has been able to
do its thing um for so many years so
you're making up ground but when you're
intentional about it it you will make up
ground quickly and you will start to
believe the things that you are saying
so please tell me I mean I know Amber
will put up the questions or maybe I'm
missing one
here let's see all right what are some
affirmations we can
use there's so many so when I teach
people about affirmations um I cater it
to their situation so um let me just use
I'll just use what I did I talked about
with this young man today um first of
all of course a classic one that so many
people can say and use is you know I
have them say their name so I will teach
the client like say your name so you
want to say like if I was doing
affirmations I would say I am a
tante and I am
enough I am a tante and I love myself
that one right right
there that one I I can
feel I see the tears I can feel the pain
in so many people's eyes because they
don't tell themselves they don't love
themselves a lot of people don't love
themselves and so when to say that every
day three times a day three yeah three
times a day it it's it's hard so that's
just an example of some but
um you know it could be I'm a tante and
I deserve to be loved I am a tante and I
am beautiful many people don't think
even pretty good-look people you would
you would be surprised that how many of
them don't think that they're beautiful
because of their negative selft talk or
whatever trauma or you know things that
they went through in their childhood
that made them not feel secure and think
that they're beautiful so that's just
some
examples
um I think that's a similar question
what are some examples of positive
affirmations we just went through that
is it better to write them in a journal
or post them absolutely you can do that
um I would say do both you can't overly
a affirm yourself we are living in a
crazy world where you do not hear
positive things about yourself every
single day like you can't overdo it you
can't overdo it you're not going to
become this prideful person walking
around like oh yeah I'm so beautiful I'm
so bad no you're just gonna to love
yourself in a healthy way and you're
going to love yourself enough that
you're not going to allow people to
mistreat you you're not going to allow
people uh you're going to you know not
allow yourself to stay in a bad
relationship because you're not being
loved or treated with respect you know
and so you know the list can go on and
on so let's say your primary caregiver
um has acts of service as a love
language okay your primary caregiver
okay so every time you say no to them it
was like saying I don't love you enough
to do
it okay the primary caregiver has acts
of
service um as a love language okay so
okay well here it
goes you have to set the boundary like
you know that that's their love language
right but even in that that you have the
right to say no in a kind respectful way
and even have a conversation with them
to let them know hey this is why I'm
saying no and I believe you know you can
even have a conversation about their
love language need but their love
language need still does not
erase you setting a boundary and being
able to pour into yourself so you're
doing the self-care for yourself and
then once you've done that then you can
come back to them and and you know if
you've done that and taken care of
yourself you should have the emotional
bandwidth and even physical strength to
be able to come back to them and say hey
I can do this for you or I can say you
know I don't have to say no so hopefully
that answers that question hopefully I
understood that
correctly
um is it correct to say if you are
uncertain
about let's see if you are uncertain
about if you want to do it then the best
thing to do is say the beautiful no
until you have time to think about it of
course or just or and you're not well
you don't have to say the beautiful no
yet because you may end up doing it but
if you're uncertain just yeah definitely
let them know communication is key to
every relationship I don't care it's not
just in a a marital relationship it is
key into every relationship honest
communication honest communication D
done in a loving respectful manner is
key to every relationship so if you're
not sure and you're uncertain let them
know say I'm not sure I'm not sure but
let me let me take some time to think
about it and then if you're a Christian
because this is you know this is we may
not have some Christians on here we know
we have a lot of them but if you're not
a Christian you're G to say well let me
think about it and if you are a
Christian you're gonna say well let me
pray about it you know so no you don't
have to say no think you know you have
the the right to say let me say a
beautiful let me think about it and I I
will let you know um so yeah yeah
so those are some of um the principles
and this is like such a big topic that I
thought like oh we do it two times but I
think especially since Dr White had to
step away uh I definitely think we could
do a third um topic I mean a third
program on this because it's
definitely
um definitely resonating with a lot of
people I want to say this one I give you
guys this one it says practicing this is
another way that she says can help
people Pleasers is practicing
assertiveness using eye statements to
express your feelings and needs Without
Blame without blaming others for example
I feel overwhelmed when I have when I
have too many
commitments
so it is okay to let people let let
people know that you're you know you're
feeling overwhelmed or you know you just
you're not able to do that like this if
I do this I will feel this way and this
will be bad for me because of this
reason um again transparency again I say
I talk about this all the time so I'm
sure you guys all know but like I have
multiple sclerosis right so when I have
to draw a line in the sand and say okay
I can't do this even though if
somebody's asking me something to do
something I have to say no I have to
take I have to have this much rest I
need to make sure that I exercise in
this way and have time to do that and I
also have to eat a certain way so and it
take might take more time to prepare
that type of meal I'm just giving an
example so I have to say well and I also
can't have a lot of stress going on in
my life so I have to say no
because Not only would I well I'll be
overwhelmed and that would physically
harm me to allow myself to get stressed
out all of the time so I'm just us
giving you an example my own examples my
own real life examples so hopefully this
resonates and you guys understand that
um so me saying the beautiful no to take
care of myself is important because I
want to be the healthiest version that I
can for myself and for my husband and
for my children and just to be in this
world as long
as God wants me here to be able to be a
blessing to others but I have to say the
beautiful no to be able to do that so um
especially as a pastor's wife sometimes
people are like ah you can't do this no
I can't it's a beautiful no so hopefully
that helps for those of you that might
be struggling um in this area and find
that it find it difficult to to use to
say the beautiful no so with that uh
let's see there's one more question and
this will be the last question is it
common for people pleaser to also have
trouble accepting no from others kind of
like I do everything for you and you
can't do this for me yes most definitely
people Pleasers uh definitely can become
can have resentment and get mad and
upset because when somebody tells them
no because there's a whole bunch of not
on boundaries going on in this
relationship or in situations and so
people pleaser I'm speaking not to out
there to whoever whoever this really
fits for people pleaser um set
boundaries so that you're you're taking
care of yourself so that when somebody
tells you no it doesn't impact you it
doesn't affect you the same because
you're taking care of yourself because
people are going to tell you no
everybody can't tell you yes and you
can't say yes to everybody so it's just
you just need a healthy a healthy
balance um and because definitely it
will affect the it can affect any
relationship that you're in if you're
not doing the beautiful no and they are
taking advantage of your people
pleasingness that's what I was going to
say people Pleasers get taken advantage
of from not such great I don't people
and I don't say like not such great
people it's just that
that people just think like oh well she
or he he always does this so I can just
you know they'll do it because they
always do it like they learn your
behavior and they take advantage of that
and that's very unfortunate but that
does
happen
so um that's what I want you guys to
remember and we're going to do a part
three because Dr White didn't get to
finish with us and I think there's a lot
more that we can just take a we can just
continue to take a deeper dive it's a
great book the disease to please um you
guys I I have the audio book I need to
get the hard cover but I have the audio
book and I can I'm encouraging you to
get it too if you want to to read more
for your for yourself um and um it's
it's a great read it's a great read um
but definitely want you thank you guys
for being here with us and I want you to
tune in next week bring it bring a
friend and share this on your social
media
um and just let them know that we talk
about all things mental health and we
have quite a library of programming
because we've been doing this almost
three years so you can always go back
and check out our other programs that Dr
White and I have done together so all
right want you guys to have a good
evening and again thank you for being
here with us have a good evening